

FRANCISCO PINTO SANTOS

Telefónica Partner Engineer | PhD Student | Lecturer

- **23-07-1998**
- **3** +34 636 627 009
- in franpintosantos
- Salamanca, Spain
 - @ franpintosantos@gmail.com
 - gandalfran
- © 0000-0002-9500-9336

INTERESTS

Backend developement

Web scraping

Software engineering

Continuous Integration

Code Generation

SKILLS

Java Spring

Node.js

Express.js

TypeScript

Python Apache Kafka

Apache Spark Flask

Django | FastAPI

MySQL PostgreSQL

Neo4J ElasticSearch

Mongo DB | Cassandra DB

cmd bash Git AWS

Azure | GitHub Actions

Docker | Kubernetes

Kibana avro Postman

OAuth2.0

SW analysis SW design

API design | API integration

Team management

LANGUAGES

Spanish: Native

English: Full professional competence

ABOUT ME

My background includes a Master's Degree in Software Engineering (2022) from the University of Salamanca, where I graduated with the highest marks and first place in promotion. I was also awarded two diplomas. I also have a Master's Degree in Smart Cities & Intelligent Buildings (2022) and a Bachelor's Degree in Computer Engineering (2020), both from the University of Salamanca, where I also graduated with the highest marks and received two degree awards, as well as the SEDEA award for the best engineering graduates at national level. I am currently working as Partner Engineer on Telefónica Kernel project, and doing research at the BISITE Research Group. I also enrich my professional experience with my teaching work as a lecturer, in several organizations such as the Pontifical University of Salamanca (UPSA), the University of Salamanca (USAL) or the Society for Economic Promotion of Gran Canaria (SPEGC). My interests include API design, creating efficient data-driven architectures and automating code generation.

EXPERIENCE

Engineer at Telefónica Kernel |Telefónica Innovación Digital

iii 01/2024 - present

- Madrid, Spain
- Assistance in the design, implementation and testing of API integrations for thirdparty partners.
- Development of mock implementations of APIs using Node.js and TypeScript.
- Troubleshooting bugs and issues in API integrations and Big Data environments.
- Working with Apache Kafka and Apache Spark for data processing and analysis.
- Assistance in the deployment and management of Docker and Kubernetes clusters for application deployments.
- Working with AWS and Azure cloud environments, including provisioning and configuring cloud resources and services.
- Assisting in the development and maintenance of documentation and support materials for partner integrations.
- Collaboration with product and engineering teams to identify and prioritize partner integration needs.
- Providing technical support and guidance to partners during the integration process.
 And building relationships with partner engineering teams to ensure successful integration and adoption of APIs.
- Staying up-to-date with emerging technologies and industry trends related to API integrations and partner engineering, and OAuth mechanisms.

Telefónica Partner Engineer | BCNC Group

i 03/2023 - 01/2024

- Madrid, Spain
- Assistance in the design, implementation and testing of API integrations for thirdparty partners.
- Development of mock implementations of APIs using Node.js and TypeScript.
- Working with AWS and Azure cloud environments, including provisioning and configuring cloud resources and services.
- Providing technical support and guidance to partners during the integration process.
 And building relationships with partner engineering teams to ensure successful integration and adoption of APIs.

Technical Team Lead & Junior Software architect | BISITE Research Group

i 08/2022 - 03/2023

- Salamanca, Spain
- Coordination of planning, design and development of R&D projects within a development team (10–15 people).
- Design, coordination, and maintenance of multiple systems as main Software architect & Cloud architect.
- Code-generation system design and implementation for agile project development.
- API REST analysis and design responsible.
- Design of web scrapers and web crawlers.

Senior full-stack developer & Team lead | BISITE Research Group

1 01/2022 - 08/2022

- Salamanca, Spain
- Coordination of planning, design and development of R&D projects within a small team (5-10 people).
- Code-generation system design and implementation for agile project development.
- Design and implementation of a human resources management application for the company.
- API rest development Python Flask-restx.
- Development of web scrapers and web crawlers.
- Web applications development with Vue.js, Node.js, Express.js and TypeScript.
- Design and development of ETL systems via Apache Kafka.
- Implementation of continuous integration systems with GitHub Actions.

Senior full-stack developer & Team lead assistant | BISITE Research Group

1 09/2020 - 12/2021

- Salamanca, Spain
- Assistant in the coordination of planning, design and development of R&D projects.
- Complete development of the deepint Python package.
- API rest development Python Flask-restx.
- Development of web scrapers and web crawlers.
- Web applications development with Vue.js, Node.js, Express.js and TypeScript.
- Design and development of ETL systems via Apache Kafka.
- Implementation of continuous integration systems with GitHub Actions.

Full-stack developer | BISITE Research Group

1 06/2019 - 09/2020

- Salamanca, Spain
- Development of web scrapers and web crawlers.
- API rest Development in Java Spring Boot and Python Flask-restx.
- Web applications development with Vue.js, Node.js, Express.js and TypeScript.
- Design and development of ETL systems via Apache Kafka.
- Implementation of continuous integration systems with GitHub Actions.

Intern student during summer | BISITE Research Group

i 06/2018 - 09/2018

- Salamanca, Spain
- API rest Development in Java Spring Boot.
- Web development with Vue.js and Webpack.
- Development of web scrapers and web crawlers.
- Design and development of ETL systems via Apache Kafka.

Intern student during summer | BISITE Research Group

i 06/2017 - 09/2017

- Salamanca, Spain
- API rest Development in Java EE and Java Spring Boot.
- Web development with Vue.js and Webpack.

LECTURER EXPERIENCE

- 📋 01/2023 present 💎 Salamanca, España
- Teaching in the area of Smart Cities Asset Management.

Lecturer | Society for the Economic Promotion of Gran Canaria (SPEGC)

1 08/2022 - 12/2022

- Salamanca, Spain
- Teaching in the subjects of introduction to artificial intelligence, Convolutional Neural Networks and Recurrent Neural Networks.

Lecturer | Pontifical University of Salamanca

i 02/2022 - 11/2022

- Salamanca, Spain
- Teaching in the subjects of database systems management, computer science fundamentals I and II.

Lecturer at Master of Internet of the Things | University of Salamanca

iii 01/2021 - present

- Salamanca, España
- Teaching in the area of IoT architectures and introduction to artificial intelligence.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Computer Science | University of Salamanca

iii 10/2022 - Present

Salamanca, Spain

M.Sc. in Smart Cities & Intelligent buildings | University of Salamanca

i 09/2021 - 09/2022

Salamanca, Spain

• GPA: 9.04

M.Sc. in software engineering | University of Salamanca

= 09/2020 - 09/2022

Salamanca, Spain

- GPA: 9.57
- Beneficiary of the academic excellence scholarship from the University of Salamanca.
- 6 calcifications with honors, including the master's thesis.
- Graduated as first of the promotion 2020-2022 with double end of studies award, granted by the University of Salamanca and the Faculty of Sciences of the same university.

B.Sc. in computer science | University of Salamanca

09/2016 - 07/2020

Salamanca, Spain

- GPA: 9.55
- Graduated as first of the promotion 2016-2020 with double end of studies award, granted by the University of Salamanca and the Faculty of Sciences of the same university.
- 25 calcifications with honors, including the bachelor's thesis.
- Beneficiary of the scholarship for collaboration with department for the 2019-2020 academic course.
- Award to the third-best academic record of the 2016-2020 promotion at national level in the field of engineering by SEDEA.
- Student representation activities for three years.

ACHIEVEMENTS

Award for the best academic record of the 2020-2022 promotion of the M.Sc. in Computer Science of the University of Salamanca.

01/2023 | Salamanca, Spain

Awarded to one of the best academic records of the 2020-2022 graduating class of the Faculty of Sciences of the University of Salamanca.

11/2022 | Salamanca, Spain

Individual mention award at Microsoft Azure hackathon organized by Viewnext IBM.

04/2022 | Salamanca, Spain

Awarded to one of the best academic records of the 2016-2020 graduating class of the Faculty of Sciences of the University of Salamanca.

11/2021 | Salamanca, Spain

Award for the best academic record of the 2016-2020 promotion of the B.Sc. in Computer Science of the University of Salamanca.

07/2021 | Salamanca, Spain

Third at the national ranking of Spain Bachelor students by SEDEA. 07/2021 | Salamanca, Spain

Member of one of the two finalist teams of the AWS hackathon organized by Viewnext IBM.

02/2020 | Salamanca, Spain

Placed as first team of Salamanca, on Google Hashcode on Everis Salamanca Hub.

02/2020 | Salamanca, Spain

Member of the winning team of the Blockchain hackathon organized by the DIGITEC project.

10/2019 | Salamanca, Spain

Member of the finalist team (Global Nominee) in the NASA Space Apps Challenge hackathon at the Everis Salamanca hub.

10/2019 | Salamanca, Spain

Member of the winning team of the smart speaker hackathon organized by Viewnext.

02/2019 | Salamanca, Spain